Jay Riley papers, 1959-1988
UCLA Library Special Collections
Jay Riley papers
1959-1988, bulk 1970s-1980s
2277
UCLA Library Special Collections
3.0 linear ft. (4 boxes, 1 carton and 1 flat box)
Jay Riley was an African American actor who started his career in 1932. He appeared in Broadway productions and also found roles in motion pictures and television. The collection consists of script material, photographs and a small amount of biographical information, press clippings, ephemera, books, and audiovisual materials related to Riley’s career.
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mercedes Riley; 2013.
Biography/History
James Merriman Riley, professionally known as Jay Flash Riley, Jay Riley, and Joe Riley, was born June 24, 1916 in Scranton, Pennsylvania. He got his start acting in 1932 with the Works Progress Administration (WPA) Federal Theater project. His first appeared on Broadway in the role of Jack Stanton in Orson Welles's production of Native Son (1941). Other Broadway appearances include Carmen Jones (1943), On the Town (1944), Finian's Rainbow (1947), The Wiz (1975), and Bubbling Brown Sugar (1976). Riley spent time in Europe (ca. mid-1960s and 1970s) and appeared in and produced a stage production of Trumpets of Our Lord. Additionally, he appeared in films such as Cleopatra and The She Beast, and did voice-overs dubbing 200-plus films. Riley's television credits include appearances on Frank's Place, Good Times, Sanford and Son, Taxi, and The White Shadow. In 1979, Riley won the Los Angeles Weekly's Lawree Award for Outstanding Performance of the Year for his role in Bubbling Brown Sugar. In 1988, shortly before his death, he appeared in the MGM film Memories of Me. He died September 20, 1988 in Los Angeles, California.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the career of African American actor Jay Riley. The majority of the materials are script materials and photographs. Additionally included are a small amount of biographical information, press clippings, ephemera, books, and audiovisual materials. Script materials represent projects for which Riley may have been involved in some capacity, such as Bubbling Brown Sugar, Trumpets of Our Lord, and The Wiz. The photographs are professional and/or personal in nature; professional photographs are mostly headshots of Riley. Notably absent from the collection are items representing his television work and his involvement with foreign-made films, such as Cleopatra and The She Beast.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged into the following series:
Series 1. Personal and Biographical Materials
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Projects
Series 4. Photographs
Series 5. Books and Audiovisual Materials
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7685605
Riley, Jay -- Archives; African American actors -- Archives
Container List
- Personal and Biographical Material., undated, 1988.
  Scope and Content
  The series consists of birth and death records, resumes, and documents related to Riley’s death. There is no specific arrangement to the series.
  - Birth and death certificates., undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Death sympathy cards., ca. 1988. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Funeral-related documents., ca. 1988. (Box 1, Folders 4)
    This file includes a memorial book, prayer certificate, and inurement program.
  - Obituary notices., 1988. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resumes., undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Address books (2 items)., undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Business cards and blank stationary., undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence., undated, 1966, 1978-1988.
  The Correspondence series consists of letters to and from Riley. The series is arranged into either personal or career related letters. Items are arranged in loose chronological order within the folders.
  - Letters to and from Riley (appear career related)., undated, 1978-1988. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    With a letter from Jerome Robbins.
  - Letters to and from Riley (appear personal)., undate, 1966, 1979-1988. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    With a card from Langston Hughes.
- Projects., ca.1959-ca.1980s.
  The bulk of the Projects series consists of script materials for projects in which Riley may have been involved in some capacity. Additionally there is a small amount of press clippings (original and photocopies), photographs, and ephemera. Materials represent projects such as Bubbling Brown Sugar, Trumpets of Our Lord, and The Wiz, among others. The series is arranged alphabetically by project title.
  - Contracts., 1983, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Residuals and handwritten notes about wages., ca. 1980s. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Riley jottings., undated. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sketches., undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Untitled project script pages., undated. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Beauty and the Beast: Promises of Someday house draft script., 1987 December 15. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blacks: A Clown Show (The) published script (2 copies)., 1960. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Black Experience (The) posters., 1972. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bubbling Brown Sugar script material, photographs, press clippings, and ephemera (7 folders)., undated, mid-1970s and mid-1980s. (Box 2, Folder 4-10, Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Checking Out script., undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dark of the Moon handbill., undated. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dirty Dancing: Just One Look pilot script., 1988. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gathering of Old Men (A) production notes., undated. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Flash and Sunda in Vaudeville press clippings (photocopies)., ca. 1939-ca. 1940. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Macbeth program and script pages., [ca. 1977]. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Memories of Me press clippings., undated. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Native Son film press kit (photocopy) and ticket., 1986 December. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - No Holds Barred script., 1988 March 2. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - On The Town photocopied page of photographs (possibly from a printed program)., undated. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pantomime (A) synopsis., undated. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    With published sheet music for Send in the Clowns and holographic notes.
  - Shakespeare in Harlem clipping of images., 1959. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sing a New Song narration script pages., undated. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Skeeters Wings script., 1988 April. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Suicide in B Flat (A Mysterious Overture) script., ca. 1979. (Box 3, Folders 12-13)
    Script annotated. With photographs, clipping, and award announcement.
  - Superior Court script pages., undated. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - There's a Boat Dat's Leavin' Soon for New York published sheet music (from Porgy and Bess)., © 1935. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Trombones script, press clipping, costume design, scene sketches, and ephemera (3 folders)., undated. (Box 3, Folders 15-16, Bin 7, Folder 4)
  - Trumpets of the Lord photographs, programs, and press., ca. mid-1960s. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Turning of Dugmore Boetie (The) script., undated. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Wiz (The) blocking script., 1975 September. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - [Working] script., undated. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Appears to be for production of Working. With photocopy of handwritten vocal score titled All the Live long Day.
  - Year in the Life (A) script., 1988 February. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Photographs and Ephemera., undated.
  The series consists of photographs and ephemera that are professional and/or personal in nature and not identified with known projects. The majority of the professional photographs are headshots of Riley. The majority of photographs are not identified. There is no specific arrangement to the series.
  - Photograph album - appears to be family and friends., undated. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photograph album - appears to be family and friends (4 envelopes)., undated. (Box 4, Folders 1-4)
    General note
    Photographs found loose in magnetic self-adhesive photoalbum. Original order could not be determined; photographs removed from album for preservation purposes.
  - Photographs - appears to be family and friends (6 envelopes and 1 folder)., undated. (Box 4, Folders 5-10, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - mostly headshots (4 folders)., undated. (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 1, Folder 13-14, Box 7)
  - Photographs - mostly with others and possibly related to projects., undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Books and Audiovisual Materials., undated.
  The series consists of books collected by Riley, and a small number of audiocassettes and videotapes. Many of the books relate to African Americans in the entertainment industry. There is no specific arrangement to the series. Audiovisual materials in this series are restricted and require advance notice for use.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Audiovisual materials (3 audiocassettes, 3 VHS, and 1 betamax)., undated. (Box 6, Folders 8-14)
    RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of audiovisual material requires production of listening and viewing copies.
    Audiovisual materials will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Books (7 items)., undated. (Box 6, Folders 1-7)
    Book titles: Black Hollywood: The Negro in Motion Pictures; Black Magic: A Pictorial History of Black Entertainers in America; Black Scenes; The Cotton Club; The New York Times Gershwin Years in Song; Negro Playwrights in the American Theatre, 1925-1959; and A Portrait of the Theatre.